Guide to the Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory Records SC1041 SC1041
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory records
1963-2009
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory.
SC1041
184320 megabyte(s)
40.75 Linear Feet
The materials consist of SAIL Dump And Restore Technique (DART) backup files, 1972-1990; digital copies of 16 mm films created from 1963-1980; handbooks; log books; manuals; and photographs and videos from the 35th SAIL reunion held in 2009.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The materials were transferred from the Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, 2011; 2016.
Information about Access
The materials are partially restricted. Users may access the public corpus of the SAIL DART files from the SAILDART website: http://saildart.com/.
Biographical/Historical note
The Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (also known as Stanford AI Lab or SAIL) is the artificial intelligence (AI) research laboratory of Stanford University. It was started in 1963 by John McCarthy, after he moved from Massachusetts Institute of Technology to Stanford. From 1965 to 1980, it was housed in the D.C. Power building, in the foothills of the Santa Cruz Mountains overlooking Stanford. During this period it was one of the leading centers for AI research. In 1980, its activities were merged into the university's Computer Science Department and it moved into Margaret Jacks Hall in the main Stanford campus. SAIL was reopened in 2004, with Sebastian Thrun becoming its new director. SAIL's 21st century mission is to "change the way we understand the world"; its researchers contribute to fields such as bioinformatics, cognition, computational geometry, computer vision, decision theory, distributed systems, game theory, general game playing, image processing, information retrieval, knowledge systems, logic, machine learning, multi-agent systems, natural language, neural networks, planning, probabilistic inference, sensor networks, and robotics.
Scope and Contents note
The materials consist of SAIL Dump And Restore Technique (DART) backup files, 1972-1990; digital copies of 16 mm films created from 1963-1980; handbooks; log books; manuals; and photographs and videos from the 35th SAIL reunion held in 2009.
Artificial intelligence.; Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory.
- Dump And Restore Technique (DART) backup tapes, 1972-1990; Series 1; 229 computer tape(s)
  Scope and Contents note
  The materials consist of 229 reels of DART tape backups. These tapes were created from 3228 original backup tapes.
  DART was a program that saved disk files on magnetic tape and restored files from tape to disk. DART was used to make periodic backups of the file disk, approximately once a week for the permanent backups.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  The materials are restricted. Users may access the public corpus of the files from the SAILDART website: http://saildart.com/.
  - Backup files, 52.6 gigabyte(s); (41,594 computer files)
    - Metadata
  - Original tapes, 0 computer tape(s)
    - P3000-P3010, 1988-1990 Mar 30 (Box 1)
    - P3010-P3019, 1990 Apr 30-May 5 (Box 2)
    - P3020-P3029, 1990 May 7-10 (Box 3)
    - P3030-P3039, 1990 May 11-18 (Box 4)
    - P3040-P3049, 1990 May 17-22 (Box 5)
    - P3050-P3059, 1990 May 22-30 (Box 6)
    - P3060-P3069, 1990 May 30-Jun 3 (Box 7)
    - P3070-P3079, 1990 Jun 4-14 (Box 8)
    - P3080-P3089, 1990 Jun 15-26 (Box 9)
    - P3090-P3099, 1990 Jun 27-Jul 1 (Box 10)
    - P3100-P3109, 1990 Jul 2-7 (Box 11)
    - P3110-P3119, 1990 Jul 7-12 (Box 12)
    - P3120-P3129, 1990 Jul 12-20 (Box 13)
    - P3130-P3139, 1990 Jul 20-26 (Box 14)
    - P3140-P3149, 1990 27 Jul-1 Aug (Box 15)
    - P3150-P3159, 1990 Aug 1-7 (Box 16)
    - P3160-P3169, 1990 Aug 7-9 (Box 17)
    - P3170-P3179, 1990 Aug 9-12 (Box 18)
  - Use copy, 2011
    Other Finding Aids note
    The public corpus of the SAIL DART files can be accessed at http://saildart.com/.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    From the DART tapes the content of 137,000 files were converted into current 2011 web formats. The exact bits are available as an octal listing of the original PDP-10 36-bit words of file content. Since larger documents and the system files were published while smaller personal files remained out of sight, the 12.3 GB of published data comprises only 14% of the file names but contains 36% of the total 33.7 GB corpus.
- Audiovisual material, 1963-1980; Series 2
  The materials are open for research.
  - Automated Pump Assembly, 1973-04; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Richard Paul, Karl Pingle, and Bob Bolles, "Automated Pump Assembly", color, sound, 5 minutes.
    Shows the hand-eye system assembling a simple automobile water pump using vision to locate the pump body and to check for errors. The parts are assembled and screws inserted, using some special tools designed for the arm. Some titles are included to help explain the film.
    Paul, Richard; Pingle, Karl
    - Use Copy
  - Avoid, 1969-03; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Gary Feldman and Donald Peiper, "Avoid", color, silent, 5 minutes.
    An illustration of Peiper's Ph.D. thesis. The problem is to move the computer controlled mechanical arm through a space filled with one or more known obstacles. The film shows the arm as it moving through various cluttered environments with fairly good success.
    Feldman, Gary; Peiper, Donald
  - Butterfinger, 1968-03; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Gary Feldman, Karl Pingle, Jeff Singer, Bill Weiher, "Butterfinger", color, sound, 8 minutes.
    Describes the state of the hand-eye system in the fall of 1967. The PDP-6 computer getting visual information from a television camera and controlling an electrical-mechanical arm solves simple tasks involving stacking blocks. The techniques of recognizing the blocks and their positions as well as controlling the arm are briefly presented. Gary Feldman supervised filming, Karl Pingle programmed the visual processing, Jeff Singer programmed arm control, Bill Weiher dealt with systems issues and this project was initiated by Les Earnest.
    Feldman, Gary
    - Use Copy
  - Cart2, 1963; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Paul W. Braisted, "Prototype Moon Rover," B&W, silent, fast motion, 9 minutes.
    Mechanical Engineering graduate student Paul W. Braisted devised a scheme to improve the controllability from Earth of a Moon rover taking into account the 2.6 second round trip communication delay. It had an analog computer that functioned as a predictor that took into account preceding steering commands and put a bright dot on the television screen at the predicted location of the cart when a current steering command would begin to take effect. With this feature the vehicle could be controlled at 5 mph (8 kph). These experiments were conducted on the playing fields of Stanford and the speed of the cart was chosen to match the sustainable jogging speed of a graduate student. For more on the Stanford Cart see http://www.stanford.edu/~learnest/cart.htm.
    Braisted, Paul W.
    - Use Copy
  - Cart4, 1979; 1 computer file(s) (mov)
    Hans Moravec, "Stanford Cart", color, silent, 1.5 minutes.
    The Stanford Cart was an experimental mobile vehicle whose television camera could move from side to side, allowing multiple views to be obtained without moving the wheels. Images were sent to a DEC KL10 computer, which interpreted the three-dimensional information and directed the cart to navigate around obstacles. The cart moved in one meter spurts punctuated by ten to fifteen minute pauses for image processing and route planning. In 1979, the cart successfully crossed a chair-filled room without human intervention in about five hours, as shown here.
  - Computer Interactive Picture Processing" (MARS Project), 1972; 1 computer file(s) (mpg)
    Lynn Quam, Robert Tucker, Bo Eross, Larry Ward, "Computer Interactive Picture Processing" (MARS Project), color, sound, 8 min.
    Describes an automated picture differencing technique for analyzing the variable surface features on Mars using data returned by the Mariner 9 spacecraft. The system used the DEC-10 timesharing computer of the Stanford Artificial Intelligence Lab (SAIL) and was used by Carl Sagan and his astronomical colleagues to detect and analyze variable features on the surface of Mars (i.e. things that changed with time).
    Ward, Larry
  - Display Simulations of 6-Legged Walking, 1972; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    D.I. Okhotsimsky & A.K. Plantonov, "Display Simulations of 6-Legged Robot Walking", Institute of Applied Mathematics -- USSR Academy of Science. Titles translated by Stanford AI Lab and edited by Suzanne Kandra. black and white, silent, 10 minutes.
    A display simulation of a 6-legged ant-like walker getting over various obstacles. The research is aimed at a planetary rover that would get around by walking. First presented at the Second CISM-IFToMM International Symposium on Theory and Practice of Robots and Manipulators, Warsaw, Poland, Sept. 1976.
    Okhotsimsky, D. I.
    - Use Copy
  - Ellis D. Kroptechev and Zeus, his Marvelous Time-Sharing System, 1967-03; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Art Eisenson and Gary Feldman, "Ellis D. Kroptechev and Zeus, his Marvelous Time-sharing System", B&W, sound, 15 minutes.
    The advantages of time-sharing over batch processing are revealed through the good offices of the Zeus time-sharing system on a PDP-1 computer. Our hero, Ellis, is saved from a fate worse than death.
    Eisenson, Art; Feldman, Gary
  - Hands, 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    - Use Copy
  - Hanoi, 1972; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Richard Paul, "Tower of Hanoi," Color, silent, 2 minutes.
    The robot hand solves the Tower of Hanoi puzzle using only four blocks instead of disks. The pauses between hand motions are due to the trajectory planning for the next move, including dynamics and control parameters, which is performed before the hand moves. Notice that the hand turns and re-grasps the block it just placed to ensure that each stack remains centered.
  - Hear! Here!, 1969-03; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Raj Reddy, Dave Espar and Art Eisenson, "Hear! Here!", color with sound, 15 minutes.
    Describes the state of the speech recognition project as of Spring, 1969. A discussion of the problems of speech recognition is followed by two real time demonstrations of the current system. The first shows the computer learning to recognize phrases and second shows how the hand-eye system may be controlled by voice commands. Commands as complicated as "Pick up the small block in the lower left-hand corner", are recognized and the tasks are carried out by the computer controlled arm.
    Produced by the Stanford Artificial Intelligence Lab; Principal Investigator: John McCarthy. Written by Raj Reddy and David Espar; photographed, directed & edited by David Espar assisted by Sheri Espar; programming by Pierre Vicens, Raj Reddy, Jeff Singer, Karl Pingle; music by Leland Smith and the PDP-6. Additional filming by Art Eisenson assisted by Mel Paul; technical advisor Gary Feldman. Sponsored in part by the Advanced Research Projects Agency (ARPA) of the U.S. Department of Defense.
    Reddy, Raj; Espar, Dave; Eisenson, Art
    - Use Copy
  - Instant Insanity, 1971-08; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Richard Paul, Karl Pingle, Jerome Feldman, & Alan Kay, "Instant Insanity" color, silent, 6 minutes.
    Shown at the Second International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI) in London.
    A computer vision system and robotic arm solve the Instant Insanity puzzle, which has been around for more than a century under various aliases. It consists of a set of four cubes with one of four colors on each of their six faces. The goal is to arrange the four cubes in a row so that all four colors appear on each of the row's four long sides. The order of the cubes doesn't matter, but that simplicity is deceptive. There are 41,472 different ways of arranging the four cubes in a row, so this is not a trivial task.
    The computer vision system first finds each of the four cubes by matching the visual edges to a prototype cube. In the case of a cube with only two faces visible, the arm turns the cube 45ยบ so that three faces will be visible. The colors of the faces are then determined by reading in the scene again under three different color filters. The cubes are then turned over so that the three hidden back faces are visible to the camera and the process repeated. Once a solution is found the computer directs the arm to stack the blocks in the required order.
  - Motion and Vision, 1972-11; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Suzanne Kandra, "Motion and Vision", color, sound, 22 minutes.
    Presentation of three research projects completed in 1972: advanced arm control by R. P. Paul, visual feedback control by A. Gill and representation and description of curved objects by G. Agin.
    Kandra, Suzanne
  - Pump, 1974; 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    Karl Pingle, Lou Paul, and Bob Bolles, "Programmable Assembly, Three Short Examples", color, sound, 8 minutes.
    The task is to mount a bearing and seal on a crankshaft. The first segment demonstrates the arm's ability to dynamically adjust for position and orientation changes. Next, the arm is shown changing tools and recovering from a run-time error. Finally, a cinematic first: two arms cooperating to assemble a hinge.
    Programming by Robert Bolles & Richard Paul, Hardware by Vic Scheinman, Filming by Karl Pingle, Sound by Kenneth Zander, Narration by Robert Bolles, Project Direction by Jerome Feldman.
    - Use Copy
  - Skyhook, 1 computer file (MPEG-2)
    - Use Copy
- Handbooks, log books, and manuals, Series 3
  - Digital Equipment Corporation, PDP-6 brochure, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1964
  - Digital Equipment Corporation, PDP-6 Handbook, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1964 Feb
  - Digital Equipment Corporation, PDP-6 Handbook, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1964 Aug
  - Digital Equipment Corporation, PDP-6 handbook, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1965
  - Steve Russell, John Sauter, Phil Petit, Dave Poole, Raj Reddy, Bill Wieher, et al., SAIL Hardware Log Book, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1967 Apr 7 - Sep 25
  - Steve Russel, John Sauter, et al., SAIL Hardware Log Book, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1967 Sep 26 - 1968 Jan 8
  - Phil Petit, Steve Russell, John Sauter, Dave Poole, et al., SAIL Hardware Log Book, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1968 Jan 8 - Mar 20
  - William Weiher, Description of the Triple-I Display Processor, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 24713
  - Digital Equipment Corporation, PDP-10 System Refence Manual, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1968
  - Brian Harvey, Monitor Command Manual, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1973 Dec
  - Martin Frost, UUO Manual, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1973 Dec
  - Les Earnest, Find a Font, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1976
  - Bruce Baumgart, Geometric Modeling for Computer Vision, 1 computer file(s) (pdf)
    - Use copy, 1974 Oct
  - Digital Equipment Corporation, PDP-6 Price List, 2 computer files (JPEG)
    - Use copy, 1964 Feb
- 35th Reunion, 2009 Nov 22; Series 4
  - Photographs, 40 computer file(s) (jpg)
  - Video
    - Entire program, 4 computer file(s) (mpg)
      General note
      Contact Public Services (e-mail: speccollref@stanford.edu) for information on accessing these digital objects.
    - Individual presentations
      Recipients of the John McCarthy award for excellence in research and research environments
      - Sebastian Thrun, Welcome to the SAIL reunion., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 28:39 min:sec
        - Use Copy
      - Sebastian Thrun, presents awards to the New-SAIL gold medalists., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 02:53 min:sec
        - Use Copy
      - Mike Montemerlo, talk, gold medal for DARPA Grand Challenge technical leadership., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 05:12 min:sec
        Mike Montemerlo was recognized for leadership and technical contributions that led to the DARPA Grand Challenge victory. Michael Montemerlo is being recognized for his leadership in Stanford Autonomous Driving Team, which led to the victory in the DARPA Grand Challenge. Mike was the chief software architect of the system, and his work influenced all aspects of Stanley's software, from hardware interfaces, perception, mapping, path planning, and control. Mike was the technical leader for the entire team, and his vision and technical strength guided all other team members in this successful project. The DARPA Grand Challenge was widely considered a milestone event for robotics. For the first time, robotic cars proved their ability to navigate extensive desert trails completely autonomously.
        - Use Copy
      - David Stavens, talk, gold medal for DARPA Grand Challenge vision algorithms., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 03:49 min:sec
        Honored for computer algorithms that led to the DARPA Grand Challenge victory. For his groundbreaking contributions to the winning DARPA Grand Challenge vehicle, and in particular his algorithms for adaptive speed control. His adaptive speed control algOlithm selected the best speed autonomously with machine learning, considering features such as road roughness, slope, and width. The algorithm could be trained to closely match a human driver's speed choices. This allowed Stanford to avoid massive human-tweaking of the race route, known as "pre-planning," that characterized some other teams. The algorithm includes a band-pass filter, designed by Gabe Hoffmann, to isolate the vehicle's suspension. David made contributions to several other aspects of the robot, including the watchdog program for software health monitoring and the adaptive vision system. In addition, David was on the launch team responsible for the vehicle on the morning of the race and, as TA for the Grand Challenge class, oversaw the very first end-to-end development of Stanley. He was also the principal safety driver for in-the-desert road tests. His other responsibilities included team coordination and media and investor relations. Using data from the event, David later published a self-taught learning algorithm that used haptic feedback from the IMU to enhance the laser perception beyond race performance.
        - Use Copy
      - Hendrik Dahlkamp, talk, gold medal for DARPA Grand Challenge "self-supervised learning"., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 03:58 min:sec
        For computer vision that led to the DARPA Grand Challenge victory. For his contributions to Stanford's autonomous vehicle Stanley, and specifically its computer vision system for long-range road detection. Called Stanford's "secret weapon" by a PBS documentary on the DARPA Grand Challenge, this system enabled Stanley to perceive and classify desert terrain in the distance as drivable or undrivable, and determine a safe traversal speed. The algorithm was a crucial contribution in two ways: First, it allowed Stanley to extend its sensing range from a classical laser-based perception range of 20 meters to a camera-based range of 40 meters, which led to a 40% increase in top speed and a win in the race. Second, it advanced a new paradigm in ru1ificial intelligence called "self-supervised learning", where the output of one sensor modality, the laser range finder, is used to generate online training data for a second sensor modality, the camera. This allowed Stanley to constantly adjust its road model to the environment, taking time-of-day, surface material, texture, shadows etc into account. Together with Intel Computer Vision Researcher Adrian Kaehler, Hendrik implemented a perception system that was able to react even to obstacles such as tank traps that it had never encountered before.
        - Use Copy
      - Pieter Abbeel, talk, gold medal for autonomous helicopter., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 07:29 min:sec
        Pieter Abbeel for acrobatic flight maneuvers of the Stanford autonomous helicopter. Autonomous helicopter flight is widely regarded to be a highly challenging control problem. It is particularly difficult to design controllers for non-stationary maneuvers in which the helicopter goes through various flight regimes, extensively exposing the great complexity of helicopter dynamics. Despite these challenges, human experts can reliably fly helicopters through a wide range of maneuvers, including aerobatic maneuvers at the edge of the helicopter's capabilities.
        Pieter Abbeel and Adam Coates developed apprenticeship learning algorithms that leverage expert demonstrations to efficiently learn good controllers for the tasks being demonstrated by an expert. These apprenticeship learning algorithms have enabled their helicopters to significantly extend the state of the art in autonomous helicopter flight and aerobatics. Their experimental results included the first autonomous execution of a wide range of maneuvers, including flips, rolls, loops, auto-rotation landings, chaos and tictocs, which only exceptional human pilots can perform. Their results also included complete air shows, which required autonomous transitions between many of these maneuvers. Their system performs as well, and often even better, than an expert human pilot.
        - Use Copy
      - Adam Coates, talk, gold medal for autonomous helicopter., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 06:25 min:sec
        Adam Coates for acrobatic flight maneuvers of the Stanford autonomous helicopter. Autonomous helicopter flight is widely regarded to be a highly challenging control problem. It is particularly difficult to design controllers for non-stationary maneuvers in which the helicopter goes through various flight regimes, extensively exposing the great complexity of helicopter dynamics. Despite these challenges, human experts can reliably fly helicopters through a wide range of maneuvers, including aerobatic maneuvers at the edge of the helicopter's capabilities.
        - Use Copy
      - Ken Salisbury, talk, gold medal for robotic hand., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 07:40 min:sec
        Ken Salisbury for the design and build-up of the Salisbury robotic hand. Ken Salisbury designed the "Salisbury Hand" (originally known as the Stanford/JPL hand) while he was a graduate student at Stanford as an advisee of Prof. Bernie Roth in Mechanical Engineering. In collaboration with Carl Ruoff at NASA/Jet Propulsion Labs and Prof. Roth, the hand was designed to be a platform for investigation of robotic grasping and dexterous manipulation. Commercialized through Ken's "Salisbury Robotics" company in the early 80's this hand became a popular research platform for many years and continues to be an icon symbolic of robotic dexterity. In the years since, Ken's labs have spawned an number of well-known robotic and haptic devices, including the MIT-W AM arm (now known as the Barrett Arm from Barrett Technology), the PHANToM Haptic Interface from Sensable Technology, telesurgical devices commercialized by Intuitive Surgical, and most recently the first version of the Personal Robot that is now being commercialized by Willow Garage.
        - Use Copy
      - Dan Klein, talk, gold medal for unsupervised probabilistic language parsing., 1 computer file(s) (m4v); 09:55 min:sec